<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A] letter to Mr Nathaniel Tenche in ansvver to a paper publish'd by him, entitul'd, Animadversions upon Mr. George White's reflection on the answer of the East-India-Company, to Mr. Samuel White's two papers; wherein the arbitrary violences committed by the said company on the lives and estates of their fellow-subjects and strangers; together with the present sad condition of their affairs in India, are occasionally intimated.</title>
            <author>White, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832378</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2142:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A] letter to Mr Nathaniel Tenche in ansvver to a paper publish'd by him, entitul'd, Animadversions upon Mr. George White's reflection on the answer of the East-India-Company, to Mr. Samuel White's two papers; wherein the arbitrary violences committed by the said company on the lives and estates of their fellow-subjects and strangers; together with the present sad condition of their affairs in India, are occasionally intimated.</title>
                  <author>White, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed, 1689</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: George White.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at head, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tench. --  Animadversions upon Mr. George White's reflection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>White, Samuel, ca. 1650-1689 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>East India Company --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LETTER<hi rend="sup">III.</hi> TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nathaniel Tenche, IN ANSWER To a PAPER publiſh'd by him, Entitul'd, <hi>Animadverſions upon Mr.</hi> George White<hi>'s Reflection on the Anſwer of the</hi> Eaſt-India-<hi>Company, to Mr.</hi> Samuel White<hi>'s Two PAPERS;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN <hi>The Arbitrary Violences</hi> Committed by the ſaid Company on the LIVES and ESTATES OF THEIR <hi>Fellow-Subjects</hi> and <hi>Strangers;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH The preſent ſad Condition of their AFFAIRS in <hi>INDIA,</hi> are occaſionally intimated.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Pulchra Laverna,</l>
               <l>Da mihi fallere, da juſtum ſanctúmque videri,</l>
               <l>Noctem peccatis, &amp; <hi>fraudibus</hi> objice nubem.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sic orat <hi>N. T.</hi> ex Horat. Epiſt. Lib. 1.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:36851:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36851:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Nathaniel Tenche,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have made me ſenſible, that 'tis my great misfortune to have utterly loſt my ſelf in your favour, by my preſuming to publiſh ſome Papers relating to the <hi>Eaſt-India Company;</hi> and I muſt confeſs I have ſince given farther cauſe to irritate your Indignation againſt me, by my ſo long delaying to render thoſe acknowledgments are juſtly due to your <hi>Judicious, Candid, and gentle Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions:</hi> But may it pleaſe you, Good Sir, to pardon my dilatorineſs for this once, and I faithfully aſſure you, I will be more expeditious for the future, when <hi>You</hi> or any of <hi>Your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> ſhall give me the like obliging Occaſion: In hopes of which your favourable Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, I will now humbly offer my grateful Sentiments of what occurs material in your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that lies before me.</p>
            <p>I find, Sir, you have taken very great offence at the endeavours I have uſed on behalf of my deceaſed Brother: But you are pleas'd to be more particularly incens'd againſt <hi>my Reflections on</hi> Davenport's Diary, <hi>and the Publiſher's Preface,</hi> which has provok'd you to that degree, that you ſeem aſtoniſh'd at the Preſumption of <hi>ſo inconſiderable a Perſon,</hi> as I am in your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Now whether you look on me with this diſdain and Scorn, either in reſpect to my diſparity with <hi>your Deputy, who is very worthy,</hi> or <hi>your more worthy Self,</hi> I will not enquire, and ſhall only anſwer this your <hi>Argument,</hi> with a Sentence I lately met with in a very good Author: <hi>Tantus quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt, Quantus apud Deum, &amp; nil amplius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It imports not therefore here ſo much to examin, <hi>What I am,</hi> as <hi>What I have done, Why I did it,</hi> and <hi>How you have animadverted upon it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the matter of Fact is truly and briefly this:</p>
            <p>My Brother, who went to <hi>India</hi> in your Companies Service, ſtaid therewith leave, not only, never did you any diſreſpect, or diſſervice; but contrarily made himſelf conſiderably uſeful to you. Notwithſtanding all this, which might juſtly give him a claim to your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Favours, was, upon your late aſſuming <hi>a Deſpotick Power and Sovereign Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> Robb'd by your Servants of above Twenty Thouſand Pounds, and loſt as much more by means of your moſt unjuſtifiable hoſtile attempts at <hi>Mergen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under all which provoking Oppreſſions I firſt ſought Relief by a private Addreſs to your Committee, in as reſpectful and humble terms, as might become your moſt ſubmiſſive Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. I need no witneſs of this, while I write to your <hi>worthy Self,</hi> who was preſent, and heard the anſwer made me by him, <hi>who wears the Name of your Governor, That 'twas the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of your Court, that what their Servants had done was juſtifiable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being thus convinc'd, that neither <hi>Juſtice</hi> nor <hi>Mercy</hi> was to be found amongſt you, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to make my Applications to our <hi>Honourable Repreſentatives in Parliament,</hi> preſenting them with the true ſtate of our moſt deplorable Caſe: And I happen'd ſuddenly after to meet a good Friend of mine, that is a Member of your Committee, who was pleas'd to offer to me, That if it ſuited with my liking, he would uſe his intereſt with <hi>your Deputy</hi> to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the matter, which, I readily accepted. But his endeavours were fruitleſs, for at next meeting he told me Sir <hi>Joſiah had taken other Meaſures;</hi> and what thoſe were, appear'd ſoon after, in his publiſhing <hi>your Friend</hi> Davenport<hi>'s foreſaid</hi> Diary, <hi>with a Preface in the Name of the Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus did <hi>your Deputy</hi> purſue the practices of his Predeceſſor <hi>Catiline,</hi> in trying to <hi>ſecure the ills he had already done by attempting greater;</hi> and his guilty Conſcience being unable to make the leaſt plauſible Defence againſt the articles of Complaint, he endeavours to ſmoother the whole matter by ſcandalous Recriminations. <hi>So I have heard of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperado Villains, who ſet fire to their Neighbours Houſes, That, in the Confuſion, they may have the more convenient opportunity to rob and plunder them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe Circumſtances ſtood the Affair; and I preſume there is no honeſt man living, but will agree, That 'twas a Duty highly incumbent on me, both in reſpect to my deceaſed Brother, and his young Children, that were fallen under my Care, to endeavour to expoſe the <hi>venomous Malice,</hi> and fruſtrate the <hi>wicked Deſigns</hi> of our Enemies. On which account
<pb facs="tcp:36851:3"/>I pub<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>occaſion'd you the trouble of <hi>Animadverting on them. Which your Herculean Labours,</hi> I now come to conſider.</p>
            <p>In the three or four firſt Paragraphs you are pleas'd to pour out your wrath upon me in a moſt Magiſterial Stile for my daring to ſpeak truth of <hi>your Deputy, your General, and your Company</hi> in expreſſions ſuitable to their Merits. Now, Sir, as I ſaid nothing then, which I am not now ready to juſtifie, ſo I dare lay it before any unprejudic'd Perſon in the World, who will but conſider the provocations I lay under; Whether I could poſſibly exceed the liberty that is allow'd to loſers, while I kept within the bounds of truth. Beſides, Sir, you know I had to do with a Man, who, as I then told you, <hi>had paſs'd with impunity through a long Courſe of Tranſgreſſions, and was thereby harden'd into a Conceit, that he was above the reach of Cenſure:</hi> So that all I did, or could, ſay; was not only excuſable, but neceſſary to awaken him out of his dreams of <hi>Deſpotick Power,</hi> and convince him <hi>that the Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates of his Fellow Subjects could no longer be bought at the rate of</hi> 10000 <hi>Guinea's per Annum to the Crown, with the additional <hi>bulky</hi> Summs, that ſtand regiſtred in your Books under the Title of <hi>Secret Services.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, Sir, is what I hope may ſerve in my defence, for whatever, <hi>thoſe Oppreſſions, which would make a wiſe man mad,</hi> may have extorted from me. And now, if 'twould not be too bold, I would take leave to ask, How it comes about, that you can, with a <hi>Salvo to your Juſtice and Prudence,</hi> commit that very thing, which, in the ſame breath, you condemn as ſo great a fault in me? But I muſt confeſs, this may ſeem an impertinent Queſtion; for I, who know, that your Company has of late not only Robb'd, but Kill'd too, with more ſecurity, than others cou'd Look on, ought not to wonder, that their <hi>Animadverter</hi> can take upon him to complain of a <hi>Mote in my Eye,</hi> before he plucks <hi>the Beam out of his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next to be obſerved is your laudable endeavours to ſupport the Credit of <hi>your Friend Davenport,</hi> and invalidate the Teſtimonies I have exhibited concerning him and his Hiſtory: wherein you have quite loſt the Character you aſſum'd, and from a pretended <hi>Animadverter,</hi> are degenerated into <hi>a baſe Perverter of Truth,</hi> having intirely laid aſide <hi>your Sincerity,</hi> and betaken your ſelf <hi>to Trick and Artifice.</hi> And this I perceive is the <hi>Maſter-piece</hi> you moſt value your ſelf upon; For you ſeem to be very much affected with a Conceit, that you have at once baffled all my Evidence. But after all your vain-glorious boaſtings, <hi>your Sophiſtry is ſtill to ſlight to deceive any but thoſe of your Fraternity, that are alike inclin'd and qualify'd with your ſelf,</hi> as will be fully evinc'd by a brief Examination of the Methods you have taken in this <hi>Evil Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YOU lead up with two very <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>wilful Errors:</hi> For firſt you ſay, I do in the beginning of my Paper cha<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> your <hi>Friend Davenport</hi> with <hi>Murder, Rapine, and Perjury,</hi> wherein you very inſidiouſly miſplace my words that you may the better confound the Senſe: for if you look over it agen, you'll find, That I there conjoyn'd <hi>Murder, Rapine, and Ingratitude,</hi> and tell you <hi>'Tis no ſtrange thing, That thoſe, who are guilty of ſuch Crimes, ſhould have recourſe to Perjury for Protection:</hi> Now if you do really miſapprehend my meaning in thoſe <hi>Metonymies,</hi> I will faithfully explain my ſelf in other words. And ſuppoſe I had begun thus:
<q>'Tis not to be wonder'd at, That <hi>He,</hi> amongſt you, who has deſtroy'd the <hi>Lives</hi> and Eſtates of ſo many Men, and has not ſpar'd even thoſe, who have moſt highly oblig'd him, ſhould try to cover his evil Actions, and ſecure the fruits of his <hi>Depredations,</hi> and <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies,</hi> by the <hi>Perjuries of His and Your Friend</hi> Davenport.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place you ſay I declare, That your aforeſaid <hi>Friend forg'd his whole Narrative,</hi> wherein you abuſe me again, and fallaciouſly interpoſe the word, <hi>Whole,</hi> which you no where find on that occaſion in my Paper, nor did I ever intend ſo. No Sir, your Friend <hi>Davenport</hi> has <hi>Cunning</hi> enough for a <hi>Committee-Man,</hi> and knows exactly well how to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weave Truth with Falſhood, that the Stuff may go off more currently. And as there are ſome things in't, which, I am ſure <hi>the Editor,</hi> as well as <hi>the Animadverter,</hi> cou'd wiſh expung'd, [I mean the Account he gives of thoſe conſiderable Concerns of my Brothers, which were afterwards pyrated by your Companies Servants] ſo what I before intended, I now reaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That, <hi>That black part, of it which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Editor to make it publick, and You to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond him in it, Was dictated and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Revenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After you have laid this falſe foundation, you go on with a Confidence becoming your Cauſe, and pronounce Sentence againſt me, That I have not made the leaſt proof of my Affirmations concerning your <hi>Friend and his Narrative;</hi> and to help make out this, you have taken the pains to <hi>winnow</hi> all my Witneſſes, and paſs your Judgment on their Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davits, wherein you have given the World a Specimen of your Parts and Principles, which the Sequel will further diſcover.</p>
            <p>What I undertook to prove, was, Firſt, That <hi>that vile Wretch</hi> Davenport <hi>was one of the moſt notorious Rogues in nature, and ſo eſteem'd by all honeſt Men, that ever had the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:36851:3"/>to be concern'd or acquainted with him:</hi> They are my very words; and to make this good, I have <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>uc'd Six credible Witneſſes, who were acquainted with his Perſon, his Practices, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Reputation, in ſundry parts of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> and here in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> and do all depoſe, that in every of thoſe Places he was guilty of ſuch horrid Crimes, and wore ſuch an infamous Character, that no honeſt Man alive would attempt to palliate or diſguiſe ſuch enormous Villanies, much leſs in any manner to take the part of ſuch a <hi>Miſcreant;</hi> only your ſuperabounding Charity, Mr. <hi>Animadverter,</hi> has inclin'd you to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge him with eaſie Cenſures. For the worſt you will ſay of him is, <hi>That he may be thought to be none of the beſt Men:</hi> But in other places you are pleas'd to ſuppoſe, <hi>He may be a good Evidence,</hi> and <hi>tax my Witneſſes with aſſiſting to defame him;</hi> and <hi>That, what they ſay, is to be look'd upon as Calumny.</hi> But what is moſt obſervable, is, <hi>The ingenuous Contrivance, you have to evade the Force of all their Depoſitions,</hi> in objecting, <hi>That they come not up to the Point,</hi> in that they do not particularly prove, <hi>That his Whole Narrative was forg'd at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of</hi> Elihu Yale <hi>at</hi> Madraſs. So that it ſeems you have taken up an Opinion (<hi>I ſuppoſe in reſpect to your Friend</hi> Davenport) That thoſe who will not, like him, Swear more than they know, What they do know, and Swear to, ſhall ſignifie nothing: For this is the very Caſe, and theſe Witneſſes have fully perform'd what I produc'd them for; but I never told you, I would bring thoſe, who knew him only in <hi>New</hi> or <hi>Old-England,</hi> or at <hi>Tonqueen, Bengal,</hi> or <hi>Siam,</hi> to make Oath, That his Narrative (<hi>which ſome of them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, never heard of) was wholly falſe, and forged;</hi> or poſitively to ſwear, <hi>What encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had in it at</hi> Madraſs (to the Name of which place, ſome of them were Strangers, and all of them here in <hi>England</hi> when 'twas done). No, Sir, 'tis only <hi>your Friend</hi> can do ſuch <hi>Miracles at ſwearing,</hi> and <hi>your Self,</hi> I think, are almoſt as expert at <hi>Shamming;</hi> as you have ſhewn us by this <hi>ſly Trick</hi> of yours; wherein, I will not adventure to judg how well <hi>your Wit</hi> ſerv'd you, but 'tis certain, <hi>your Honeſty</hi> was abſent on ſome other occaſions.</p>
            <p>Having therefore by my foreſaid Witneſſes, prov'd this Friend of yours to be <hi>Rogue enough in general;</hi> It now comes to be enquir'd into, whether I have by any other Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies given ſufficient proof, <hi>That he has committed Perjury in his foreſaid Narrative, by forging his malicious Stories to wreak his Revenge on my Brother, for chaſtiſing him according to his Demerits;</hi> Which was the ſecond thing I undertook. And for this, I bring Five more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Perſons, who all poſitively Swear, <hi>That to their certain knowledg, ſeveral things in his ſaid Narrative, are falſe and ſcandalous Lyes.</hi> They all likewiſe depoſe, <hi>That he was at</hi> Siam, <hi>(as in all other places) esteem'd a muſt treacherous Villain.</hi> And Three of them affirm, <hi>That my Brother had ſome time before, publickly whipt and impriſon'd him for his Rogueries, in revenge whereof, they verily believe he forg'd thoſe Calumnies againſt him.</hi> And now let us ſee, by what <hi>Legerdemain</hi> you try to ſhift off theſe Evidences.</p>
            <p>Why, one of them is a <hi>bold intereſted Affidavit-Man,</hi> and you make ſo bold with him, to ſay, he is <hi>almoſt,</hi> if not <hi>altogether, forſworn;</hi> which is a Point I'll leave him to diſpute with you, and will trouble my ſelf with no further anſwer to that, and your other ſcurrilous Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, on thoſe, who have in this Affair, been Friends to Truth and Me, than to tell you, <hi>That they are all of them in ſome reſpect, and ſome of them in all reſpects, far your Betters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another of theſe Witneſſes you are pleas'd to object againſt, for <hi>That he was</hi> Phaulkon<hi>'s and Mr.</hi> White<hi>'s Dear Friend, and</hi> beſides that Crime, <hi>he Swears not ſo much to particulars, as would bear Weight in a Court of Judicature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Three others, you knock down at once by affirming, <hi>They were Deſerters from your Companies Service:</hi> Which, by the way, is ſuch a <hi>groundleſs Forgery,</hi> that I cannot forbear to reprehend you for it <hi>in your own Language,</hi> and Declare, <hi>That you are therein a Villanous Calumniator, and the Lye remains upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I paſs on to the Third thing I affirm'd, which was, <hi>That your Friend</hi> Davenport <hi>was encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and abetted in his Villanous Proceedings againſt my Brother, by</hi> Elihu Yale <hi>at</hi> Madraſs. And this I readily confeſs is not poſitively aſſerted in any of the Depoſitions; nor is it eſſential to the main matter of the truth or falſity of the Narrative, <hi>But 'tis nevertheleſs true,</hi> and I have made it ſufficiently appear to any reaſonable Man, by the Intimations I have given. But if you will ſtill be pleas'd to doubt it, I refer you to any intelligent Perſon, that came home formerly on the <hi>Beaufort,</hi> or ſince on the <hi>Bengal,</hi> who were at <hi>Madraſs,</hi> when the <hi>Curtana</hi> return'd, and they will acquaint you, <hi>That when your Friend</hi> Davenport <hi>was, at his arrival there, ſcorn'd and ſhun'd, as a moſt deteſtable Villain, by every one that had any regard to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations: He was yet highly careſs'd, and admitted to many private midnight Audiences by the Honourable</hi> Yale; And afterwards had the favour done <hi>him, (by the way of your Court of Juſtice)</hi> to force about a Hundred Pounds from my Brother's Correſpondent, on no other Evidence, but his own ſingle Oath, <hi>That my Brother was ſo much his Debtor.</hi> And, as to the reaſon I aſſign for theſe Endeavours of <hi>Yale's, in reſpect of the guilt that lay upon him for his Treacher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dealing with the King of</hi> Siam <hi>in a parcel of Jewels;</hi> If you doubt of that, I commend you
<pb facs="tcp:36851:4"/>to no other Perſon, than <hi>your worthy Deputy</hi> for farther Satisfaction, who in a Letter of his to his <hi>ſaid Creature,</hi> tells him, in relation to this Affair, <hi>That 'twas a very <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>k Buſineſs, but he would bring him off of it.</hi> Which joyful News did ſo tranſport <hi>Elihu,</hi> Tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cou'd not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to communicate it to his Companions, and ſo it came to the Cognizance of an honeſt Gentleman there, who has writ my Brother the Account of it. And by the ſame good hand I am likewiſe acquainted how <hi>your Friend Davenport</hi> after all his meritorious Services, took his laſt leave of <hi>Madraſs,</hi> which, becauſe it may be of uſe to you in your next <hi>Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions;</hi> I will tranſcribe <hi>Verbatim,</hi> and ſo conclude this <hi>Vile Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND now to make an end with this brave Fellow</hi> Davenport, <hi>I will tell you after all how he went off from this Place. Mr.</hi> Robert Freeman <hi>having formerly been ſo kind to him at</hi> Metchlepatam, <hi>to credit him with about fifty Pagoda's, and thinking it juſt to be repaid, gave a power to Mr.</hi> Philip Noden <hi>to receive the ſame, if he met him in his Voyage to</hi> Pegu, <hi>as he happily did; But found</hi> Davenport <hi>ſo ill provided, that he cou'd not comply: Which Mr.</hi> Noden <hi>at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn acquainted Mr.</hi> Freeman <hi>with: Who, to ſecure his Debt afterwards, endeavour'd to attach the Money in Court out of what</hi> Davenport <hi>had recovered of your Friend Mr.</hi> Lucas <hi>on your Account. But</hi> Davenport, <hi>whoſe faculty ſeldom fail'd, for a Legerdemain Trick, had one ready for that, and publickly declar'd in Court, and made offer to make Oath, That he had paid the ſaid Debt before to Mr.</hi> Noden (<hi>who was then gone a Second Voyage to</hi> Pegu) <hi>and that he had a full Diſcharge for it, which was unhappily loſt with his other Papers at</hi> Mergen, <hi>and being then in great Credit, and deſerved favour with our Great ones, for what good Service he had done againſt you and Captain</hi> Weltden, <hi>and what other turns he was to ſerve: Our Judge, with as unparallel'd Wiſdom, as Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, took</hi> Davenport<hi>'s Word in his own Cauſe, and inſtead of allowing Mr.</hi> Freeman <hi>to ſecure his Debt, gave</hi> Davenport <hi>your Moneys in Mr.</hi> Lucas<hi>'s hands, as you have been before acquainted. But as the old ſaying is, Murder will out, and he that is a Knave is commonly diſcover'd to be a Fool; it happened by good Providence Mr.</hi> Noden <hi>arriv'd here from his Second</hi> Pegu <hi>Voyage, and had detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Villany, and offer'd Perjury of</hi> Davenport, <hi>which he conſcious of, durſt not ſtay the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but before Mr.</hi> Noden <hi>cou'd get aſhoar, ſlipt off privately, and got on board a</hi> Portugueze <hi>Ship then juſt ready to Sail for</hi> Bengal, <hi>and ſo we loſt this honeſt mans good Company, which hath ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd our very Judge; That after ſo many Nine days are over, he does now begin to See, and cannot forbear ſaying to almoſt everybody,</hi> I do now in my Conſcience <hi>believe this</hi> Daven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <hi>is a very Rogue indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HAVING thus <hi>evacuated</hi> your Encomiums on <hi>your Friend,</hi> and <hi>your Animadverſions</hi> on my Evidence, I will now take a brief View of the fine work you have made with my Reflections on the <hi>Editors</hi> Preface.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning <hi>your Companies War with Siam;</hi> You take notice that I gave it the name of <hi>a wicked thing,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>I would publiſh a Narrative to prove it ſo,</hi> which, you there at firſt promiſe to anſwer; But it ſeems you afterwards better bethought your ſelf, for at the cloſe of your Paper, you acknowledge I have publiſhed ſuch <hi>a Narrative,</hi> and ſay, <hi>'Tis not proper for you to reply to't, but that I ſhall have a full anſwer in due time before my Superiours; <hi>A moſt Ingenious Animadverſion,</hi>
               </hi> which in plain Engliſh ſignifies neither more nor leſs, than, That, <hi>Since you have perus'd my Paper, you find it impoſſible to make any plauſible Defence for that moſt unjuſt and irrational Proceeding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You next obſerve, That I am much offended at the <hi>Editor</hi>'s endeavours to diſparage and leſſen <hi>my Lord Phaulkon,</hi> and that I expos'd that ridiculous Objection, of <hi>his having been formerly a poor fellow and Stewards Mate of a ſmall Ship,</hi> which I now again tell you, <hi>ſavours more of the Philoſophy and Morals of a Porter, than a Man that pretends to <hi>Deſpotick Power.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to my <hi>Lord Phaulkon</hi>'s declaring himſelf to be of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> (wherein, by the way, he was baptized and educated under his Parents who always were of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion), 'Tis true, I paſs'd it over in ſilence, as not accounting ſo malicious an impertinence worthy any anſwer. But I confeſs there are ſome other heavy Charges the <hi>Editor</hi> has exhibited againſt him; which I could no way excuſe or palliate, as, <hi>That he not only made curious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of great value to the Pope and the French King, But (what is worſt of all) to the late King</hi> James <hi>and his Queen alſo;</hi> which, tho I own to be a moſt unpardonable Crime in him, yet I muſt needs ſay, I think the <hi>Editor</hi> was no very proper Perſon to be his <hi>Accuſer,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you know, <hi>There is a certain Man in the World, whom he loves as well as he can poſſibly do himſelf, That has preſented the ſaid late King with ſeveral</hi> 10000 <hi>Guineas, for no other end than to facilitate his obtaining a moſt illegal and Arbitrary Power over the Lives, Liberties and Eſtates of his fellow Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing you offer at, is to try if you can frame ſomething that may look like a Juſtification of <hi>your Companies late exorbitant Actions:</hi> And all you have to ſay is, <hi>They are warranted by their Charter;</hi> whereto I need give no other anſwer, <hi>(conſidering I write to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36851:4"/>who I perceive is ſo well read in our Engliſh Chronicles)</hi> than to tell you, That if <hi>they</hi> amongſt you, who did firſt procure, or have ſince put in practice thoſe illegal Powers, had their due deſerts: <hi>They would not be the firſt Traytors, that have been <hi>Ty'd up</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of the King's Authority to oppreſs their Fellow-Subjects.</hi> And here to bring this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the more home to you, I will tell you of a paſſage at Court, as I had it from a Perſon of great worth and good intelligence.</p>
            <p>When your <hi>faithful Deputy</hi> had by his <hi>Golden Arguments</hi> convinc'd the <hi>late King and ſome of his Miniſters,</hi> That 'twas indiſpenſibly requiſite he ſhou'd have a Commiſſion to <hi>execute Martial Law</hi> over thoſe, to whom he has lately given the new Name of <hi>The Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Subjects under the King:</hi> His Majeſty ſent for the Lord Chancellour, and order'd him to let ſuch an Inſtrument paſs the Broad Seal; And (tho you know he was not noted <hi>to he over tender of the peoples Rights</hi>) yet he ſeem'd very much ſurpriz'd at ſo ſtrange a thing, and made anſwer, <hi>That it cou'd not be done;</hi> urging it as a moſt intolerable Violation of the Law, and uſing many arguments to diſſuade the King from it, till at length he was told, <hi>Well, I will hear no more againſt it, but it ſhall be done,</hi> which charm'd him into <hi>Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> and when he next went to Court, being ask'd, whether 'twas accordingly executed; He reply'd, <hi>Yes Sir, and Your Majeſty may now hang Sir</hi> Joſiah Child <hi>when you pleaſe, For he has committed Treaſon in perſuading you to this thing: <hi>Ergo Cave.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing that diſpleaſes you is the freedom I take to admoniſh the <hi>Editor of the Traiterous Notions he has infus'd into his new made General,</hi> and the friendly Advice I gave him to refrain ſuch dangerous Extravagancies, by the Example of a Citizen, that was hang'd in <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth's time for a much more pardonable Preſumption; For if that unhappy Man fool'd away his Life, by ſaying, <hi>His Son was Heir to the Crown; though he only meant his own Houſe, which was known by that Sign, and ſo ſeems more guilty of Vanity than Malice:</hi> Of what puniſhment ſhall we Judge him Worthy, who has not only aſſum'd to himſelf, but delegated to his dependents, <hi>A Deſpotick Power and Sovereign Authority?</hi> And yet you are pleas'd to ſay <hi>I brought in that Story by Head and Shoulders,</hi> and <hi>that it has no allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the matter;</hi> And very angry you are with me for it. But however you chanced to be then ſo much out of humor, I cannot doubt, but when you think of it again, and <hi>conſider Rightly,</hi> you will make me a return of thanks, <hi>for that ſeaſonable Advice, and ſuitable Inſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with theſe your reſpects to the <hi>Editor,</hi> you make your ſelf alſo an Advocate for his <hi>new made General,</hi> and accuſe me of ſlandering him in ſtiling his Actions <hi>Little leſs than High Treaſon, without inſtancing in any particular, wherein he has aſſum'd an unwarrantable Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> Which ſtrange paſſage inclines me to believe you ſcarce ever gave your ſelf the trouble to read over that paper of mine you have undertaken to <hi>Animadvert</hi> upon: Or otherwiſe, I cou'd not in my own Juſtification omit to treat you once more <hi>in your own Stile,</hi> and tell you <hi>the Lye remains upon You:</hi> For if you pleaſe to take the pains to look over it again, You will there find a brief Intimation of the <hi>Piracy and Felony he committed on the Eſtate of Captain</hi> Valentine Pynes, <hi>in the Seiſure of his Ship and Goods to amount of about</hi> 3000 <hi>l.</hi> And ſince you give me this Occaſion, I will call no other perſon than <hi>your own good Self,</hi> to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt him in that matter; For I hear you was one of the <hi>Select Committee</hi> upon this Buſineſs, and I have had ſome general Notices how the affair was manag'd, <hi>As That you never vouchſafed the Captain the favor of a hearing (which by the way I muſt tell you, was a method of proceeding, that would better have become Turks than Chriſtians)</hi> But after you had conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the merits of the Cauſe, according to your good pleaſure, you let him know your <hi>Deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Determination, <hi>That upon his giving an Authentick full Releaſe to Your General, and all his Confederates,</hi> you would condeſcend <hi>to reſtore him</hi> 1300 <hi>l.</hi> NOW what I argue from this, is, <hi>That either you do therein tacitly confeſs your General had done him wrong,</hi> or elſe, <hi>you cannot excuſe your ſelf from doing wrong to the Company, in giving him ſo much Money, which was lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs.</hi> This is impartially the ſtate of the Caſe; And ſo I leave you to vindicate your <hi>Celebrated Probity and Piety,</hi> from thoſe Imputations, to which, this unhappy affair has ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd you obnoxious; and when you take the matter in hand, I pray go through with it, and let us alſo know, why you gave him neither <hi>more nor leſs, than the juſt Sum of</hi> 1300 <hi>l.</hi> Becauſe I'm ſure he can make it fully Evident, That he was at firſt robb'd of double that Amount, beſides the vaſt Prejudice that accru'd to him by thoſe inhumane Uſages of your <hi>New made General,</hi> in being ſo long deprived of the Uſe of his Stock, and put out of that beneficial way of Buſineſs he was placed in.</p>
            <p>Your next Objection againſt me, is, <hi>That I ſeem to juſtifie thoſe, that, you are pleas'd, to term the Rebels at St.</hi> Helena, and you adventure to affirm, <hi>That 'twas fully prov'd, before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons; That the poor People there were guilty of a <hi>Horrid Rebellion:</hi>
               </hi> Which is ſo notorious a <hi>Falſity,</hi> that I will, in kindneſs to you, Suppoſe you were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at that Hearing, but have been abus'd and led into this Error by your <hi>Faithful Deputy,</hi> who did at that time <hi>make his Parts and Innocence equally apparent.</hi> But the Real Truth, is, That, inſtead of a pretended <hi>Horrid Rebellion</hi> there, it appear'd to be a <hi>moſt Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36851:5"/>Murder,</hi> contriv'd and carry'd on by ſome of your Brethren here, who were therefore <hi>number'd amongſt the moſt Execrable Criminals,</hi> and by a Vote of the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſe <hi>excluded from the general Act of Indemnity now depending: Nor will our Land be purg'd from the <hi>crying Guilt of Blood,</hi> till <hi>He,</hi> or They, who projected and perpetrated thoſe barbarous Murders, be brought to condign puniſhment.</hi> Let me therefore here, Sir, offer you the Advice of a Friend, who wiſhes well to his very Enemy, and perſwade you, if you were not at the bottom of this <hi>black buſineſs (as I think you did not then move in that Sphere, wherein you have ſince made your ſelf ſo eminent)</hi> That you will not now be tempted to <hi>defile your hands with Blood,</hi> and ſo bring <hi>the Curſe of God on Your Self and your Poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You next inveigh againſt me for alledging, <hi>That your Company was indebted vaſt Sums to the Merchants in</hi> Surrat, <hi>at their leaving that place,</hi> and ſay, <hi>'Tis notoriouſly falſe; for upon ſearch of the Companies Records, you find they owed no ſuch vaſt Sums, and that little they did owe, they were not only able, but ready and willing to pay, even during the War.</hi> Now what <hi>Records</hi> you were permitted to peruſe, or what you call a <hi>vaſt Sum,</hi> I cann't tell; but this I ſtill affirm, <hi>That,</hi> when <hi>your General gave them the Go-by, your Company</hi> was <hi>really indebted</hi> to the Merchants there, above 300000 <hi>l. ſterl.</hi> And beſides many other Proofs I can make, I refer you for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmation of this particular, <hi>to the Books made up by</hi> Bartholomew Harris <hi>at</hi> Surrat, Anno 1686. And then as to what you offer, <hi>of the Companies readineſs to pay it during the War;</hi> I can only anſwer you, that there are ſome Men in the World have arriv'd to that high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Aſſurance, <hi>That they can glory in their very Shame.</hi> And for an Example, I will tell you the truth of this thing, which is, That after your <hi>new made General,</hi> had, without any previous Declaration of War, poſſeſs'd himſelf of about Twelve <hi>Surrat</hi> Ships richly laden, he did in <hi>September</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> 1687. ſend word to the <hi>Companies Creditors, That he was now ready to pay them, bidding them take notice, That if they did not come or ſend to</hi> Bombay, <hi>to receive their Mony; the Intereſt ſhould ceaſe:</hi> To which the Merchants made anſwer, <hi>They lent their Mony in</hi> Surrat, <hi>where it ought to be repaid them;</hi> and the current Diſcourſe amongſt them on this occaſion was, <hi>That,</hi> Lency <hi>intended to pay them with one band, and rob them with the other. Vae vobis!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to <hi>your new-coin'd Proverb,</hi> of <hi>Purchaſing the Whetſtone,</hi> wherewith you think you have <hi>ſharpen</hi>'d your Anſwer to my Affirmation, <hi>That your General did by a baſe Fraud trapan the</hi> Surrat Ships <hi>into his Snare, in giving them the Security of the Companies Paſſes, and afterwards making Prize of thoſe very effects.</hi> Which, I ſaid, <hi>I cou'd prove by a Gentleman of good Worth and Credit, that had it from your Deputy's own Mouth:</hi> But you ſay, <hi>I find upon enquiry, there was no ſuch thing utter'd by the Deputy Governour to any Man,</hi> and that's all one, as if you had ſaid, <hi>I ask'd the Deputy, and he deny'd it,</hi> which, I think, is one of the <hi>blunteſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers</hi> that ever was pretended to be <hi>whetſton'd.</hi> For, pray Sir, conſider, what a fine World we ſhould live in, if every Criminal that pleads <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> ſhould therefore be acquitted? But here to put you upon bringing this matter to a ſpeedy iſſue, becauſe you ſomewhere threaten me, <hi>That my Slanders ſhall be examin'd more judicially,</hi> I will give the advantage of an Action againſt me, in affirming poſitively, <hi>That your Deputy, Sir</hi> Joſiah Child, <hi>did relate that matter as I aſſerted it, in the ſixth Page of my Reflections, and I will prove it ſo.</hi> And now the World will judg him <hi>Innocent or Guilty,</hi> as he either proſecutes me for a <hi>Scandal,</hi> or by <hi>ſilence,</hi> gives conſent to the truth of my Allegation againſt him.</p>
            <p>The next thing that preſents it ſelf, is, the proſpect of juſt ſuch another Rarity as, <hi>Homer's iliads in a Nutſhel,</hi> being no leſs matter crowded into one ſingle Clauſe, than <hi>a full Catalogue of all the Right Honorable Companies Dominions, Territories, Sovereignties, Iſlands, Forts, Cities, Towns, large Factories, and other Buildings.</hi> And now that the <hi>Verity,</hi> as well as the <hi>Validity</hi> of your Hiſtory, may be the more conſpicuous, I will inſert the whole Paragraph, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer you my opinion concerning the import thereof.</p>
            <p>[That Argument alledged by the Author of the Companies Defence, to juſtifie, <q>That it is requiſite they ſhould have in <hi>India</hi> a Sovereign power, over all People under their Government, as the Dutch have (although at the ſame time ſome of them be reſpectively their fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi>) becauſe of thoſe Towns and Dominions they have there, in Sovereignty under His Majeſty, remains invincible; Notwithſtanding all the ſlight inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Gentleman, That they have but one Town call'd <hi>Madraſs</hi> (which every body that knows any thing of the Engliſh concern in <hi>India,</hi> knows to be falſe) they having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſaid City of <hi>Madraſs</hi> and Fort St. <hi>George,</hi> two entire Iſlands <hi>Bombay</hi> and St. <hi>Helena,</hi> and two Forts, Towns, and Sovereignties, upon the Weſt Coaſt of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> Viz. <hi>Bencoolen,</hi> and <hi>Indrapoora;</hi> with ſufficient Territories belonging to both, as much as the Company did deſire, or is requiſite for the Good of <hi>England:</hi> The like Town, <hi>Fort, &amp;c.</hi> at <hi>Carwarr</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Mallabar:</hi> The like at <hi>Retora,</hi> in the Queen of <hi>Attingas</hi> Country; And by this time, the Company hope, and have given Order for the like Fort, &amp;c. to be erected in the <hi>Gingee</hi> Country; And the Town of <hi>Chuttanuttee</hi> in the Bay of <hi>Bengal,</hi> granted to the Company for a <hi>Bank ſall,</hi> upon making the Peace with the <hi>Mogul,</hi> after the laſt War. Beſide large Facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb facs="tcp:36851:5"/>and other Buildings at <hi>Coddolore, Port Novo, Conimere, Metchlepatam, Pettipolee, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapolam, Vizagapatam, Ballaſore, Hughley, Caſſambuzar, Malda Dacca, Pattana, Rajamaul, Tonqueen</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Tonqueen</hi> near <hi>China, Amoy</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>China, Broach, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licut, Tillichery, Suratt</hi> and <hi>Swally,</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>India,</hi> and <hi>Mallabar;</hi> And in <hi>Perſia</hi> at <hi>Gombroon, Shyraz,</hi> and <hi>Spahaun,</hi> as alſo at the ancient City of <hi>Balſora,</hi> far up the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> now under the Dominion of the Grand Seignior.]</q> 
               <hi>Thus far You.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I pray let me eake it out a little farther with this Diſtich,
<q>
                  <l>And ſundry fine Caſtles they have built in the Air,</l>
                  <l>As uſeful and ſtrong as any ſtand there.</l>
               </q> Which my <hi>Poetry</hi> matches exactly well with your <hi>Proſe;</hi> for they are both alike, <hi>fantaſtical Chimera</hi>'s. And here, Sir, I muſt deal plainly with you, that you may no longer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd your ſelf, nor others by your Miſreports; for indeed, you have in this paſſage mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, <hi>That you are groſly ignorant of the true ſtate of your Companies Affairs in</hi> India, <hi>and that you have been impos'd upon by <hi>Somebody,</hi> to write as you are bid:</hi> For I declare, and will prove, <hi>That the major part of what you have aſſerted, is either directly falſe, or very vain and frivolous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, as to <hi>Fort St. George,</hi> and <hi>your City (as you will have it)</hi> of <hi>Madraſs,</hi> you may if you pleaſe call it by <hi>Twenty ſeveral Names;</hi> but I aſſure you, of my own certain knowledg, <hi>'tis all one and the ſelf-ſame thing;</hi> and in my opinion, 'tis the moſt important Settlement the Company have yet attain'd in all <hi>India,</hi> which by a continu'd good management, would have arriv'd to be a conſiderable <hi>Emporium.</hi> It firſt began to flouriſh under the Government of Sir <hi>William Langhorn, who found it without one Ship belonging to the Port, but left it with a conſiderable Fleet,</hi> and by his <hi>judicious Conduct,</hi> and <hi>indefatigable Induſtry,</hi> the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> did in his time <hi>correſpondently increaſe,</hi> as it afterwards proceeded under his Succeſſors, till about ſix. Years paſt, when thoſe <hi>fatal Orders</hi> were ſent out by <hi>your Committee,</hi> and ſtrengthned with more powerful Mandates in private Letters from <hi>your Deputy,</hi> whereby that great Work is ſince deſtroy'd and ruin'd, which with ſo much Wiſdom, Art, and Care, and by ſuch laudable Endeavours and Adventures, had been brought to ſo good effect, I mean, <hi>Your Tyrannous Oppreſſions of the Inhabitants with moſt unjuſt and intolerable Taxes and Impoſitions,</hi> which has put a general Damp and Diſcouragement on all, and driven many away from the place, moſt of the <hi>Portuguezes</hi> of account and value being already remov'd to the neighbouring Town of St. <hi>Thoma,</hi> to put themſelves under the protection of the <hi>more merciful Mahumetans,</hi> and the reſt are preparing to follow; not is there any hope of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, unleſs the late <hi>profound Project</hi> of erecting a <hi>Court of Aldermen,</hi> and conjoyning them therein with the <hi>Hebrew Merchants</hi> and the <hi>Heathen Merchants,</hi> ſhou'd overcome all other difficulties, and invite them to reſettle in <hi>your new made City.</hi> I could here alſo tell you how much the <hi>Arbitrary Violences</hi> committed in your <hi>miſ call'd Court of Juſtice,</hi> has contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the <hi>general Diſſatisfaction;</hi> for I poſitively affirm, and oblige my ſelf to prove ſuch <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Sentences</hi> paſt there by <hi>your temporizing Judg, Sir</hi> John Biggs, that render him as void of <hi>Senſe,</hi> as <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And here likewiſe I cou'd make an enquiry, to which I am ſure you can give me no rational Anſwer; If I ſhould ask <hi>What honeſt Policy there was in ſending out the foreſaid Hebrew Merchants? (For ſo I hear your Deputy has lately chriſtned the Jews)</hi> and he, I confeſs, is the only Man alive can tell us what Advantage has accru'd by giving them the opportunity <hi>to thruſt our Countrymen out of the Diamond Trade.</hi> But alas, there has many more ſuch <hi>kind Offices</hi> been done <hi>the Engliſh</hi> there, and I muſt not omit <hi>one amazing thing,</hi> that came lately to my knowledg, 'Tis <hi>The new-faſhion'd Poll-Money, of</hi> 12 l. <hi>a Head, that is by your <hi>Deſpotick Power</hi> demanded of every Perſon before he is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to embarque for his Native Country;</hi> and was accordingly forc'd from thoſe who came lately on the <hi>Bengal Merchant,</hi> for which the <hi>Honorable Elihu</hi> gave them Receipts, as appears by a true Copy of one I tranſcrib'd from the Original:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Fort St.</hi> George, <date>October <hi>the 11th.</hi> 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>REceiv'd then of Mr. <hi>Tho. Goar</hi> the Summ of Twenty Six Pagoda's, for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Right Honourable Company; Being for permiſſion to take his paſſage on Ship <hi>Bengal</hi> Merchant, for <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>per <hi>Elihu Yale.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Nay with ſuch <hi>inhumane Rigour</hi> is this exacted, That <hi>Mr. James Harding,</hi> who went out in the Company's Service, and ſo continued ſeveral years, but afterwards <hi>by his fault and misfortune together</hi> fell to decay, was deny'd leave to return home to his relations on that Ship, <hi>becauſe of his inability to pay that Barbarous Taxation,</hi> and ſo is detain'd there in a moſt indigent Condition. This I have from ſo good a hand, that I dare aver the truth of it: <hi>And now I challenge you out of all your Reading and Converſation, to produce an Inſtance of the like prodigious Inſolence, and unnatural Cruelty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36851:6"/>
            <p> As to your <hi>Iſland of Bombay,</hi> 'tis according to its name, <hi>a very good Harbour,</hi> and ſo may be occaſionally uſeful, as well when we return to our <hi>old honeſt Trade of Merchandize,</hi> as it hath lately been to <hi>your Company in thoſe felonious Violences they have acted on the</hi> Mogul<hi>'s Subjects by ſurprizing their Ships:</hi> And I doubt not but by a prudent Management, and good uſage of the Inhabitants, and thoſe, who would thereby be invited to reſort thither, 'twould ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch an Income to the Publick, as might countervail the charge of keeping it. But if you entertain any ſuch <hi>idle Notions,</hi> as <hi>That by all the ſtrength and power you have,</hi> or <hi>can have there, you will prevail to remove the Mart of Trade from</hi> Surrat <hi>to that place, you are but in a Dream,</hi> and <hi>Embrace a Cloud for</hi> Juno: And let me here tell you, you will find all your vain Dependence on your <hi>Force,</hi> and your no leſs <hi>fooliſh,</hi> than <hi>wicked</hi> aſpirings to <hi>Territories</hi> and <hi>Dominions</hi> in thoſe Parts, not only <hi>to fail your Expectations;</hi> But, if the Government here does not ſpeedily and effectually interpoſe to prevent it, <hi>You will thereby ſerve the Nation ſuch a <hi>Dog Trick,</hi> as the Dog ſerv'd himſelf in the Fable, by an entire Loſs of that noble and beneficial Commerce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is the Iſland of <hi>St. Helena,</hi> which, methinks, you ſhou'd not mention without <hi>a deep Sigh, and a ſhower of Tears, for the many horrid Murders committed there, by your Companies means and directions.</hi> And then, as to the <hi>Place,</hi> becauſe you foiſt it into the number of thoſe, you wou'd have to be underſtood <hi>of conſiderable Trade and Buſineſs in</hi> India, leſt you ſhou'd have been ſo miſinform'd, I muſt tell you the Truth, That, <hi>'tis a ſmall ſpot of Earth on this ſide the</hi> Cape, which, in the firſt Deſignation, was intended for nothing elſe, <hi>but an Inn, for the Ships to bait at in their return;</hi> Nor had <hi>your Company</hi> the leaſt pretence to any Trade there more than in <hi>Butchers Meat,</hi> till about Six years ſince, <hi>they ſent over a bloody Villain to <hi>Butcher Mankind.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to your two famous Forts on the <hi>Weſt Coaſt of</hi> Sumatra, <hi>Bencoolen,</hi> and <hi>Indrapoora,</hi> where you ſay <hi>you have two Towns, and ſufficient Territories, as much as the Company did deſire, or is requiſite for the good of</hi> England: But I muſt firſt anſwer you, that inſtead of boaſting of what you have there, Your Company has Cauſe <hi>to be aſham'd of the Occaſion, that put them upon ſetling at that place,</hi> which was <hi>by the irreparable Prejudice they did the Nation in throwing themſelves out of their moſt commodious Settlement at <hi>Bantam,</hi>
               </hi> as I have already prov'd in a Paper I formerly publiſh'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And now as to thoſe your <hi>new Reſidences</hi> on which you beſtow ſuch <hi>Rhetorical Floriſhes,</hi> I muſt tell you, <hi>They were formerly excepted in</hi> Charter par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>as Places ſo notorious for their unhealthineſs, that it look'd like Death to all, and prov'd really ſo to moſt of our Countrymen, who were ſo unhappy to go to them.</hi> Nor has it ſince far'd better with thoſe you have employ'd thither in your late Expeditions; for the <hi>Soldiers</hi> and <hi>Factors</hi> have died as faſt as they cou'd be ſent, and no one Ship has remain'd any time in Port without the loſs of many Seamen, and ſome by a <hi>general Mortality</hi> have been quite diſabled, which has verified the Old Saying, <hi>That every Corn of Pepper coſts a Drop of</hi> Engliſh <hi>Blood.</hi> Then as to your <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> there; you ſay you have two <hi>Forts,</hi> and I will tell you of what <hi>Force</hi> they are; That at <hi>Bencoolen</hi> has about twenty Guns mounted on a Bank of Earth, and by laſt Advices had about Ten <hi>Europeans</hi> and thirty <hi>Blacks</hi> remaining alive; but that at <hi>Indrapoora</hi> has no Force at all. You talk alſo of <hi>two Towns; but thoſe, at my Poetry told you before, ſtand in the Air:</hi> and as for your <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> 'tis only in your <hi>Conceit;</hi> for your abode there is but <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> and the Natives can diſlodge you whenever they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>But now we come a ſecond time to the place, where <hi>you have <hi>purchas'd the Whetſtone,</hi>
               </hi> which has ſet your <hi>Tools</hi> on ſuch an <hi>edge, that you ſharp upon us to ſome purpoſe:</hi> In telling us, <hi>That the Company have order'd a Fort to be erected at the Town of</hi> Chutanutte <hi>in the Bay of</hi> Bengal, <hi>which was granted to them for a Bank Sall, upon making the peace with the Mogull after the laſt War.</hi> And here 'tis very obſervable to ſee how luckily it falls out, That <hi>your Friend</hi> Davenport <hi>ſhould ſo occaſionally (as I before intimated) return to that place in the very nick of time to ſerve you in the Government of your new Gariſon there.</hi> Nor can I here omit to take notice of thoſe <hi>falſe Rumours</hi> have been induſtriouſly ſpread abroad both by <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> to contradict this good news of yours: in telling us, <hi>That your affairs in the</hi> Bay <hi>were all ſtill in a moſt dreadful confuſion, and that inſtead of erecting Forts, the Government there does utterly refuſe to readmit your Servants till full ſatisfaction is render'd for the Murders and <hi>Depredations</hi> they have committed.</hi> For thus the <hi>ill people at Madraſs</hi> write by the <hi>Bengal Merchant,</hi> and the <hi>Rocheſter;</hi> and <hi>thoſe ill people</hi> that are come home on both thoſe Ships <hi>ſay the ſame thing:</hi> Which makes me believe <hi>they are all in Combination againſt the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Company, being envious at their wiſe Management and ſucceſsful progreſs of their Affairs:</hi> Nay, <hi>I doubt they are Interlopers in their hearts, and I wiſh it be not at laſt found out, That they have received as large Bribes from the</hi> Dutch Eaſt-India <hi>Company, as thoſe did who lately petition'd the Parliament againſt you:</hi> For I will not doubt but their are all <hi>malicious Flams,</hi> and yours the <hi>Real Truth;</hi> Only for the confirmation of my faith in this point, I deſire you will be pleas'd to reſolve me <hi>At what time the Firſt War ended, becauſe you here mention the
<pb facs="tcp:36851:6"/>ending of the Laſt War?</hi> And pray <hi>let me know, Which of the Wars we muſt call This that ſtill remains on foot, and is now ſo vigorouſly proſecuted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus having viſited all your <hi>Forts, Towns</hi> and <hi>Territories,</hi> I now come to your <hi>Large Factories</hi> and <hi>other buildings;</hi> And I begin, as you do, with <hi>Coddolore and Porta Nova,</hi> where your Company never had any <hi>Factories</hi> or <hi>other Buildings,</hi> but what they Rented; and about two years ſince, they quitted thoſe places, as they likewiſe have withdrawn from <hi>Metchlepatam, Pettipolee,</hi> and <hi>Maddapollam;</hi> As for <hi>Ballaſore, Hugley, Caſambuzar, Malda, Dacca, Pattana,</hi> and <hi>Rajamall,</hi> they all depend on your <hi>War</hi> or <hi>Peace</hi> with the <hi>Mogull,</hi> And therefore when you have reſolv'd the Inquiries I made in the cloſe of the preceding Paragraph, we ſhall know whether they <hi>ſtand</hi> or <hi>are fallen;</hi> And the like of <hi>Broach, Swalley</hi> and <hi>Surrat.</hi> At <hi>Amoy on the Coaſt of China,</hi> you have had no ſetled Factory for ſome years paſt, and have lately <hi>farm'd out that Trade to a ſort of Interlopers at the rate of</hi> 10 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> And as to the Three Factories you ſpake of in <hi>Perſia,</hi> if you had known the true Story of your Companies affairs in that Kingdom, you wou'd ha' been aſham'd to give that intimation; For I'm ſure that for twenty years together they negotiated no Merchandize worth naming at any of thoſe places. But to their <hi>Eternal Infamy they have irrecoverably leſt their juſt Right and Title to a moiety of the Cuſtoms at the Port of</hi> Gombroom, <hi>which was granted to their Predeceſſors, for aſiſting the</hi> Perſians <hi>to retake</hi> Ormuz <hi>from the</hi> Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueze.</p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Ancient City of</hi> Balſora, which you let us know <hi>is far up the great River Euphrates,</hi> your Company have not I'm ſure had any <hi>ſetled Factory</hi> there for many years paſt, nor made any uſe of that Port, till <hi>the</hi> Modena <hi>was lately ſent thither on the Honourable Deſign of taking the</hi> Surratt <hi>Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND now I have given you this fair Account of things, which <hi>I will juſtifie before all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers,</hi> I appeal to your own ſelf, whether you have not been baſely betray'd by <hi>him</hi> that was Your <hi>Dictator,</hi> who took advantage of your being ſo grea a Stranger to theſe Affairs, <hi>and ſo put upon you to publiſh what he pleas'd.</hi> But we are all thus ſubject to be abus'd, <hi>when we will be medling with what we do not underſtand;</hi> Not that you are therefore the leſs qualify'd to be <hi>a Member of the preſent Committee;</hi> But (as the Caſe now ſtands) rather the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, <hi>For your ignorance is the Mother of your Devotion to your worthy Deputy,</hi> and has created in you <hi>a Venerable Eſteem for him;</hi> Ay, And 'tis that likewiſe has inſpir'd you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That, ſince you have ſearch'd more narrowly into his Conduct of the Companies Affairs, and are more experienced in the affairs of</hi> India, <hi>you have found nothing but what is Prudent, Juſt and Honourable.</hi> And I pray when you write again remember that you add <hi>Generous</hi> alſo, which, above all, he highly deſerves at your hand <hi>for that magnificent Preſent of</hi> 50 l. <hi>per Cent. he has lately beſtow'd on you and your Brethren.</hi> There want not ſome Envious Detractors we know, who repine at your proſperity, and wou'd fain perſuade us to believe <hi>he has done this to ſecure what he cou'd of a deſperate ſtake, and to be beforehand with your Creditors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is conſcious to himſelf, That all the Effects the Company have in the whole World cannot near diſcharge their vaſt Debts at home and abroad, beſides the great Demands that many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd perſons make, and ſtill cheriſh ſome hopes of reparation.</hi> But let them all ſay what they will, notwithſtanding this <hi>aſtoniſhing Dividend, with the loſs of the Nathaniel, and the Diſmal news of War and Confuſion in India; <hi>Stock is ſtill really worth as much as 'twas before.</hi> Ask</hi> John Sewell <hi>elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it only remains, That I take notice how much you <hi>ſtomach it,</hi> that I ſhould intimate, <hi>There are ſome of your Brethren of the Committee, who hold their Places on condition that their Conſciences are at the Deputy's Command.</hi> Which you ſay you take to be a <hi>Reflection</hi> on <hi>your ſelf,</hi> and ſo by the way I cannot but obſerve, <hi>That Guilt does oft make ſtrange Diſcoveries.</hi> But what is ſtill much more obſervable, is that <hi>ingenious Innuendo,</hi> whereby you wou'd bring it about, That I am guilty of a <hi>Scandal</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>Noble Peers, who are pleas'd to condeſcend to ſit among you. <hi>But hold Mr. Animadverter,</hi>
               </hi> This ſly Trick won't ſerve the Turn you deſign it for, but rather gives me an opportunity to do my ſelf the honor of letting the World know, <hi>I have had the happineſs of a more Gentleman-like Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, than to be ignorant of that humble Reſpect and Deference due to the Dignity of thoſe moſt Honorable Perſonages.</hi> And if it wou'd not make you ſick with Envy, I could further tell you, There are ſeveral <hi>Noble Lords</hi> in the Kingdom that do not diſdain ſometimes to admit me to their Converſation: ſo that I will not doubt but 'twill ſuffice to take the <hi>Sting</hi> out of this your <hi>malicious Suggeſtion,</hi> That I here ſolemnly declare and proteſt, <hi>It has been as far from my Thoughts to deſign the least Detraction from any of thoſe Noble Peers that permit their Names to be inſerted in the Liſt of your Committee, as 'tis from my Intentions to rake in the Duſt of my dead Father.</hi> And now I have taken this Occaſion to tell you <hi>how much I am a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> you ſhall likewiſe know I am a <hi>free born Engliſh-man too,</hi> and will not be afraid to tell <hi>You</hi> and the reſt of your <hi>Fraternity</hi> that are my <hi>Fellow-Commoners,</hi> I ſay my <hi>Fellows</hi> (for tho you may be <hi>Older,</hi> or <hi>Richer,</hi> or more <hi>Cunning,</hi> yet the Law has included us all in the
<pb facs="tcp:36851:7"/>ſame Claſſis) <hi rend="margQuotes">That every one of you, who takes upon him to juſtifie the illegal Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in ſeizing my Brother's Eſtate, and is not really and readily inclin'd to make intire Reſtitution thereof, is therein a moſt diſhoneſt Man.</hi> Nay, that I may further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you how much I ſlight your Judicial Menaces, I will be more plain and particular in declaring, That Sir <hi>Joſiah Child,</hi> your Deputy, Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Tenche</hi> himſelf, and Sir <hi>Ben. Bathurſt, who wears the Name of your Governor,</hi> are, all Three of you, in caſe you perſiſt to juſtifie thoſe Depredations, Guilty of Aiding, Abetting, and aſſiſting <hi>Pirates</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> and of <hi>receiving and detaining</hi> plunder'd Goods. <hi>So take it amongſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I cloſe all with thoſe Words of mine, which you borrow'd in the beginning of yours: and I affirm, That the <hi>profligate Age</hi> we live in has not produc'd a greater <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy of Villany,</hi> than to ſee a <hi>Man,</hi> who wou'd fain be thought to be <hi>Somebody</hi> in this World, and makes a <hi>ſhew</hi> of <hi>ſanctimonious Preparations for a better,</hi> and is withal arrived even to the Age of <hi>Muſt-Die:</hi> Yet that under all theſe Circumſtances He ſhould appear <hi>a publick Patronizer of the moſt flagitious Crimes, and employ his Time and Talent to aſſiſt in the Opreſſion of <hi>injur'd Orphans;</hi>
               </hi> Which I recommend to your <hi>quotidian</hi> Conſideration, immediately before your <hi>Mattins</hi> and <hi>Veſpers;</hi> and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>YOURS, Not as You deſerve, <hi>George White.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
